Finding Aid for First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1833-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1833-1992, 1875-1978
First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
(in 7 boxes)
5.5 linear feet
86971 Ba 2
Methodist church established in Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1827; proceedings and minutes of various church boards and committees; baptism and marriage records, topical files relating to church activities and personalities; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church (donor no. 7178 ) in various accessions.
Further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The first Methodist circuit rider to preach in the Ann Arbor area was John Baughman. Two years later, in 1827, five individuals organized themselves into a Methodist Society. In 1830, the Ann Arbor church was listed as an appointment of the Methodist Conference. The first dedicated building of the church was begun in 1837. In 1866, the congregation having outgrown this facility began construction of a new church building on the corner of State and Washington. In 1939, this building was replaced with a stone structure at the same location.
The records of the First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor, Michigan include Church registers; Governance records; Topical Files; and Photographs. Included are proceedings and minutes of the Board of Stewards, Board of Trustees, Official Board, church committees, and quarterly and annual conferences; correspondence and reports of the Methodist Educational Advance; membership lists and directories; baptism and marriage records; financial information; missionary materials, including those about Ann Arbor native Judson Collins, first Methodist missionary to China; documents related to church history; and other church materials, including a limited number of photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; United Methodist Church (U.S.)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First United Methodist Church of Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Methodist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Parades and processions.; Temperance--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Church Registers (marriages, membership, baptisms)
  - Marriage Record Book 1868-1930 (Box 1)
  - Baptism Record Book 1869-1905 (Box 1)
  - Membership Record Book circa 1888-1905 (Box 1)
  - Membership Record Book circa 1855-1900s (Box 1)
  - Mixed purpose volume, including membership lists 1940s (Box 1)
- Governance Records
  - Board of Stewards Proceedings
    - 1883-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1919-1929 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Minutes 1834-1858 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1883-1940 (Box 2)
    - Minutes October 1973 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  - Activities Reports 1919, 1937, 1951 (Box 3)
    (for Sunday Schools, Phoebe Beal Circle, Women's Home Missionary Society, etc.)
  - Administrative Board
    - Minutes January-February 1968, May-October 1969, October 1977; also Report to the Congregation, September 1970 (Box 3)
    - Minutes November 1971-December 1978 (with gaps) (Box 3)
  - All Church Conference October 1977-April 1978 (Box 3)
  - All Family Church Night 1939 (program and radio script) (Box 3)
  - Annual Church Conference January 1978 (Box 3)
  - Annual Report 1918, 1920-1921 (Box 3)
  - Board of Stewards
    - Annual reports 1873-1874, 1875-1876; board members, 1927, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Minutes and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      Summary of recent activities, undated; resolution 1885; financial information, 1937; Beal resignation, 1937; minutes, 1962, 1963, 1965 (with gaps); acknowledgement of gifts 1967
  - Boy Scouts: Troop Four
    - Correspondence, histories, clippings, reunion information, activities summaries, member lists, mostly from the 1920s, 1960s (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous February 1988 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1989, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Budgets 1924-1946 (with gaps), 1952-1953, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Building Valuation 1960 (Box 3)
  - Bulletins, Programs, Weekly Reminders
    - Undated Pre-1900 (Box 3)
    - 1901-1939 (Box 3)
    - 1940-1972 (Box 3)
    - April 1892-June 1987 (with gaps) (Box 3)
  - Bylaws 1938 (Box 3)
  - City Council October-November 1976 (Box 3)
  - Clippings (mostly re: building projects) (Box 3)
  - Coalition of churches 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    (clipping, brief summary, Administrative Board action)
  - Collins, Judson Dwight, first Methodist Missionary to China
    - Miscellaneous materials 1937 (Box 3)
      (commemorative services correspondence, a picture story of Collins by Bible School children, personal reminiscence by an acquaintance, biographical skit)
      (see also Missionary Work)
    - Anniversary materials May 1987 (Box 3)
  - Collins, Reverend Wellington (brother of Judson) (Box 3)
    (contains notes taken by Wellington from various history books)
  - Committees
    - Committees (general descriptions) March 1976 (Box 3)
    - Archives and Historical Committee Minutes June 1985-May 1987 and highlights (Box 3)
      (with gaps)
    - Building Committee
      - 1920s-1940s undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
        (on loan to the donor)
      - 1950s (Box 3)
    - Finance Committee
      - Parish group meetings packet, includes finance plan 1932-1933 (Box 3)
    - Membership lists of Committees 1935-1936; 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Minutes of Assorted Committees
      - 1963 (Box 3)
      - 1964 (Box 3)
      - 1965 (Box 3)
    - Nominations and Personnel Committee Minutes 1975 April-1978 September (Box 3)
      (incomplete)
    - Social Concerns Committee
      - 1964-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - 1969 (Box 3)
      - 1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1972 (Box 3)
  - Commission on Education Annual Report, Spring 1954 (Box 4)
  - Council of Ministries Minutes February 1972-February 1979 (with gaps) (Box 4)
  - Conferences: Detroit, and Quarterly 1833-1958, 4 folders (Box 4)
    Includes resolution 1884; correspondence, 1930s; report, 1959; minutes, 1833-1842, 1909, 1912-1916, 1919, 1921, 1923, 1925, 1930, 1933, 1938, 1963)
  - Debt Financing: Records of Shareholders 1885, bound volume (Box 4)
  - Directories and Lists: includes pre 1900, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Education Work Area
    - Minutes February 1971-May 1973 (with gaps) (Box 4)
    - Minutes February 1971-December 1974 (with gaps) (Box 4)
  - Epworth League 1931-1932 (Box 4)
    (program, correspondence re: trip to Thumb Lake, state league information)
  - Estates and Wills, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Executive Council minutes October 1921, December 1921, January 1922, April 1922, June 1934 (Box 5)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary of Groundbreaking and Building Dedication 1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Financial Plan undated (probably 1933) (Box 5)
  - Financial Reports/Statements 1911, 1933-1934, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
  - Foreign Missionaries 1871-1938 (Box 5)
  - Future of First Church Committee Minutes January 1975-October 1978 (Box 5)
  - General Conference: commentary, "Size of General Conference" undated (Box 5)
  - Historical Documents
    - Indentures, articles of incorporation, programs, savings account books, contracts (Box 5)
    - Clippings and parish directory 1867-1988 (Box 5)
    - 1856 Deed and Pew Rental Book, circa 1904-1912 (Box 5)
  - History, 3 folders (Box 5)
    (includes history by Mary Luny, 1937 and histories of various church societies and clubs)
  - House By the Side of the Road (County Service Center) undated (Box 5)
  - Lenten Devotions of Parishioners 1986 (Box 5)
  - Cheng Guam Lim (clippings, incomplete) 1986 (Box 5)
  - Men's Activities post-1900 (Box 5)
    (mostly promotional materials)
  - Methodist Educational Advance (reports and correspondence)
    - 1922 (Box 5)
    - January-June 1923 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1923 (Box 5)
    - January-June 1924 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1924 (Box 5)
    - 1925 (Box 5)
    - 1926 (Box 5)
    - 1927 (Box 5)
    - 1928 (Box 5)
  - Methodist Men Handbook undated (Box 5)
  - Missionary Work (Box 5)
    (Includes lists of missionaries; insightful letter from missionary in India in 1920 and an interesting photo/biographical album on church missionaries)
  - Music Program 1919-1933 (Box 5)
    (choir costs 1922-1923; correspondence with new music director, 1919, 1933)
  - Music October 1977 (Box 5)
  - Music 1987-1992 (Box 5)
  - Official Board: Resolution on attendance-undated; call for retreat 1937; minutes (with gaps) 1921, 1937-1939, 1963-1965, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Organizational Pamphlets/Charts Undated 1975 (Box 5)
  - Pastoral Prayer (regarding Gulf War) January 13, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Pastors
    - Abbey, Merrill: biographical data, clippings, sermon 1958 (Box 5)
    - Fisher, Frederick (Box 5)
      (Includes biographical data, memorial tribute, letter of resignation and response, and article "A Bishop Seeks Soul Freedom")
    - Large, Dwight: (Box 5)
      (biographical data, suggestions for action follow-ups to sermons, incoming correspondence re: decision to accept pastorship)
    - Ninde, Edward: five-year report 1900-1905; report 1900-1901 (Box 5)
    - Rupert, Hoover: mostly clippings, sermons (Box 5)
    - Stalker, Arthur W. (Box 5)
      (biographical data, obituaries, memorial tributes, letter of welcome to his successor)
    - Strobe, Donald B.
      - Sermons 1973 May-1986 October (Box 5)
      - Retirement 1990 (Box 5)
  - Pastor-Parish Minutes February 1974-July 1978 (Box 5)
  - Peace Pole 1989 (Box 5)
  - Pew Holders (with maps of pew locations) 1900-1915 (Box 5)
    (see Historical Documents folders for indentures)
  - Profile of Membership, Attendance, Finances 1974 (Box 5)
    (prepared for visit by Dr. Shaller, Naperville, Illinois)
  - Promenade November 1986 (Box 6)
  - Publications
    - The Flyer, 1978-1987 (with gaps) (Box 6)
    - Methodist Messenger
      - 1935, 1938, 1952-1962 (with gaps) (Box 6)
      - 1962-1967 (with gaps) (Box 6)
      - 1968-1975 (with gaps) (Box 6)
      - 1975-1978 (with gaps) (Box 6)
    - Newscast July September-November, 1941 (Box 6)
    - Focus on Youth, November 1974 (Box 6)
    - Lay Hold on Hope: a Lenten devotional booklet for 1991 (Box 6)
    - Golden Anniversary Directory 1990 (Box 6)
  - Religious Census: University of Michigan 1920s (Box 6)
  - "Report To Lay Conference" (Box 6)
    (no date, no author)
  - Sesquicentennial (summary of events; church history information) (Box 6)
  - Stephen Ministry 1989, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Survey of Plant, Equipment, Finances, and Activities 1933-1934 (Box 6)
    (see also Building Committee, 1930s)
  - Temperance undated, 1883, 1935 (Box 6)
    (Includes program from Anti-Saloon League of Michigan meeting, undated; Reverend R. Pope sermon, 1883 letter from pastor to University of Michigan President Ruthven re: cocktail grill advertisement in student directory, 1935)
  - Wesley Foundation 1920s-1940s, 1977 (Box 6)
    (Includes programs 1940s; financial information, 1920s; trustees meeting minutes, 1929-1931, 1938; miscellaneous reports and correspondence 1930-1931; correspondence re: building use, 1977)
  - Wesleyan Guild 1890-1917 (Box 6)
    (Includes pamphlets, undated, 1890-1911; handwritten constitution for women's guild, undated; correspondence of Board, 1916-1917
  - Youth (clippings) 1962-1968, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Visual Materials
  - Glass Projection Slides, includes one set of positive images, incomplete and of poor quality
    - Ann Arbor Scenes (Box 7)
    - Church, exterior (Box 7)
    - Floor Plans (Box 7)
    - Group, unidentified (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    Photos illustrating church activities and personalities; also photos showing temperance march in downtown Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1910s.
    - Boy Scouts 1967 (Box 7)
    - Chapel-in-Round Dedication undated (Box 7)
    - Choir (adult and junior) undated (Box 7)
    - Christmas Activities 1952, undated (Box 7)
    - Church of 1866 interior and exterior, undated (Box 7)
      (includes photo of 1906 fire)
    - Church of 1937
      - Exterior (Box 7)
      - Interior (includes floor plan) (Box 7)
    - Groundbreaking and Laying of Cornerstone Ceremonies 1939-1940 (Box 7)
    - Men's Class 1919 (Box 7)
    - Missionary Work (Box 7)
    - Organ 1940, undated (Box 7)
    - Parsonages undated (Box 7)
    - Pastors
      - Rupert, Hoover (Box 7)
      - Stalker, A.W. and family (Box 7)
    - People
      - Groups (most identified) 1912-1987, undated (Box 7)
      - Individuals (most identified) 1940-1964, undated (Box 7)
    - Promenade Dedication undated (Box 7)
    - Sculpture by Carleton Angell (Box 7)
    - Temperance Marches in Ann Arbor (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)